<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mynd and exposition of that excellente learned man Martyn Bucer, vppon these wordes of S. Mathew: Woo be to the wordle [sic] bycause of offences. Math. xviij. Faythfully translated in to Englishe, by a faythfull brother, with certayne obiections [and] answeres to the same</title>
            <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848055</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 487:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mynd and exposition of that excellente learned man Martyn Bucer, vppon these wordes of S. Mathew: Woo be to the wordle [sic] bycause of offences. Math. xviij. Faythfully translated in to Englishe, by a faythfull brother, with certayne obiections [and] answeres to the same</title>
                  <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. van der Erve],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴, A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The mynd and expoſition of that excellente learned man Martyn Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer / vppon theſe wordes of S. Mathew: <q rend="inline">Woo be to the wordle bycauſe of offences. <bibl>Math. xviij.</bibl>
               </q> Faythfully tranſlated in to Engliſhe, by a faythfull brother, with certayne obiections &amp; anſweres to the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mathew. 15.</bibl> Euerye plante that my heauenly Father hathe not planted, ſhall be pluckt vp by the rotes.</q>
            <p>¶ Printed at Emden. 1566.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the godlie Reader.</head>
            <p>VNderſtandinge (dearly beloued in the Lord Ieſus) by a faithfull brother, of the contention that nowe is in my natiue countrie, concerninge popiſh apparrell and ceremonies, to the greate greife &amp; ſorowe of the godlie, and to the reioyſinge of the enemies, (whiche hopeth dayly for the reſt of theyr father dregges) I thought it mete (as one wyſhing good to my countrie) to tranſlate the worke of that excellent inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente of the Lordes vinyarde Martyn Bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer, entreatinge vpon the wordes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyour, wrytten by S. Mathew in the .xviij chap. ſayenge: Woo be vnto the wordle by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of offences: wherin he declareth not only what an offence is, &amp; how it is taken, but alſo as occaſione dothe ſerue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning rites and ceremonies of the churche, to the great comfort of the godlye. Wylling and requyring that ye ſtand faſt in the lybertie, wherwith Chriſt Ieſus hath made you free and wrappe not your ſelues in the yoke of bondage. For it is not nowe tyme to ſlippe backe from the lybertie of the Goſpell, but manfully to abyde therin, yea euen, though it be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyfe to confirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame as worthie ſouldiars in Chriſtes church, alwaies lokin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge for the comyng of our Sauyour Ieſus</p>
            <trailer>Thus fare ye well.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The mynd and expoſition of that excellente learned man Martin Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, vppon thes wordes of Mathew: Woo be to the world, becauſe of offences. Math. xviij.</head>
            <p>HEre Chriſt ſpeaketh not of ſuche offences as the good are wonte to geue vnto the euill, but of ſuche as the euill geue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, or to thoſe that endevour to become good &amp; godlye. Theſe offences (as may be gathered by the places of ſcripture which make mencion therof) are what thinges ſo euer be ſpoken or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, geuinge any occaſion of ſynne, either becauſe they are euyll of them ſelues, or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les becauſe they are not diſcretly done and accordinge to Chriſtian charitie. For this cauſe Paul in the .2. epiſt. &amp; .6. chap. to the Corinth. exhortynge vs, that in nothynge we geue occaſion of offence, dothe declare by thoſe thinges which he mencioneth by &amp; by after, that then we geue no offence at all, when we approue our ſelues in all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges as the miniſters of God: that is to ſay, when we ſo behaue our ſelues in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which we either ſpeake or do, that they may make to edification and appeare to be done in the ſpirite of Chriſt. Where vppon
<pb facs="tcp:13129:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> we may take that to be an offence,<note place="margin">the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of an offence.</note> what ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer we ſay or do that maketh not to the furtherance of Godes glorie and the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of our brethren, procedyng of a ſound and vnfayned fayth and ordred accordinge to ſyncere and true loue.</p>
            <p>Nowe this mynde and purpoſe all the wicked haue not, I meane to do all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the glorie of God and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of men: and therfore not only all that they ſpeake or do may well be called offences, but they themſelues alſo becauſe their who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le lyfe is nothinge elles but an offence, are of the Lord hym ſelf before in the .13. chap. called an offence. Seynge therfore the world is nowe full of ſuch offendors, it is not without great cauſe that the Lord here ſaith: It is nedfull that offences ſhould co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. For ſeyng there be ſo many euill trees, there muſte needes be great abundance of euill fruite alſo. Moreouer euen the verie electe, becauſe they are neuer free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, being alwaies compelled to ſay: Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs oure treſpaſſes, as we forgyue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs, do gyue many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of offence, when ſo euer they ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke or do any thyng that procedeth not of faith and loue. Therfore Paul exhorteth and beſeche thoſe men to beware that they
<pb facs="tcp:13129:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> receiue not the grace of God in vayne, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing occaſion of offence to no man. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs alſo to the ſame thinge as often as he willeth vs to walke circumſpectlie &amp; warely folowing in all thinges the will of God. For we are planted to this ende, that we ſhould beare fruite, and bringe many to true righteouſnes and godlines. wherfore yf we committe any thinge either in word or deed, which tendeth not to this ende, we geue therin occaſion of offence, and do con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie to our vocation: and forſakinge the kyngdom of Chriſt, we promote the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan: which thinge howe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible it ys for a Chriſtian man to do, who ſeeth not? For this cauſe S. Paul in the xiiij. to the Rom. and in the .j. epiſt. &amp; .viij. chap. to the Corint. Vehemently deteſteth euen thoſe offences which they that vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly vſe the Chriſtian libertie gyue vnto the weake by ſuche thinges as of themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in dede are not euyll, but yet are not done accordinge to charitie.</p>
            <p>When the newe Teſtament was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the bloude of Chriſt emonges the electe, wher ſoeuer they were, and of what ſtocke and kynred ſo euer they came, and that without any law of ceremonies: then were all rites and ceremonies included in
<pb facs="tcp:13129:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> the precepte of loue, &amp; all kyndes of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and dayes were made then alike. But yet when many of the Iewes were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto Chriſte, theyr faith was more weake then that they durſt vſe this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. They abhorred all ſuch meates as we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re forbydden by Moſes lawe, and ſpecially ſuch as were offered to ydolles: And this was the infirmitie of theyr faith, that they were not perſuaded, that to the faythfull nothyng can be vnpure. Nowe, thoſe that of loue had no regard or verie litle, which ſeeketh in all thinges the ſaluation of our neighboures, dyd eate all kyndes of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the preſence of all men, hauyng no reſpecte to the infirmitie of faith in many, and ſo they gaue vnto them a dowble of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. For either they cauſed them through their contempt to fale to variance and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde with them, or elles they allured them to vſe the like libertie, but yet with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fayth, ſo that they wold not ſticke to eate all kyndes of meates indifferently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe theyr conſciences dyd perſwade them that it was ſynne ſo to do. Agaynſt the firſte offence Paul wryteth Ro. 14. Yf (ſaith he) by occaſion of meate thy brother be greued, thou walkeſt not nowe charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie. Concernyng the ſecond offence, thus
<pb facs="tcp:13129:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> he writeth: albeit he addeth ſomwhat alſo touchinge the fyrſt: All thinges in deed are pure, but it is euyll for the man that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with offence, it is good neither to eate fleſſh neither to drinck wyne, nor any thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge elles wherby thy brother ſtumbleth or is offended, or made weake. Wher he ſaith he ſtumbleth, I vnderſtand that to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the firſt kynde of offence, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning variance and diſcord. Where he ſayth, he is offended: I vnderſtande that of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kynde of offence, in that he vſinge his libertie peruerſely, &amp; by his example draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hym that is more weake to do the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, is to hym as a ſnare, whyles he geueth hym an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate that thinge againſt his conſcience, which he iudgeth not to be lawfull. And where he ſaith, or els is made weake, I iudge that to be ſpoken of thoſe men, who ſeing their brother do that thing which (as they are yet ꝑſuaded) is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of God, do not turne ſo farre backe that they will fale to variaunce and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention with them, neither do they follow that with they thynke to be euyll and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully done: but yet they are greued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane tyme, and beare leſſe zeale and loue to the goſpell and the mainteyners therof, eſpecially ſuch as then vſe the liberty ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:13129:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> and this in dede is to be made weake.</p>
            <p>Nowe a godly and a charitable brother rather then he would that this ſhould come to paſſe, ought to auoyd the vſe of all vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie thinges, becauſe the kyngdome of God is not meate and drynke, but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, peace, and joye in the Holy Goſte: Much more ought he then rather neuer to eate fleſhe, then by his libertie to geue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to his brother ſo to ſtumble that he ſhould therby either fale in to an hatred &amp; contempt of hym, or elles contrarie to his fayth and conſcience ſhould attempte to do the ſame thinges that he doth. In deede S. Paul in the firſt epiſtle and .8. chapt. to the Corinth. ſpeakinge of this later kynde of offence, concludeth in this maner: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if meate offende my brother, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eate fleſhe whiles the world ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>But we muſt note in all theſe thinges, that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually vſeth the name of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For of that plante whiche the father hath not planted, that is, of the reprobate, we muſte haue no regarde: Whom in dede the more godly you are, the more you ſhall offende. This therfore muſte be our cheife entente and purpoſe, ſo to do and order all thynges that they make to the edifyeng of our brethren. So ſhall it come to paſſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:13129:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſome tymes we ſhall ſee cauſe to vſe oure libertie, and ſome tymes not to vſe it. For when wordes are to be approued by deedes, the libertie that is preached muſt nedes be confirmed with examples. This dyd Peter and Barnabas with certeyne other Iewes very godly at Antioch. And therfore when they diſſembled the ſame agayne for feare of ſuch as came from Iames, Paul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode Peter openly and blamed hym vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently. Gal. ij. This example ought to be well conſydered. For if Peter in this ſlyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perye place tooke a fale, what is he that ought not herin to be carefull, &amp; take good heede of the lyke daunger: They that came from Iames, were brethren: and therfore it ſemed that it was better for them not to touch any fleſhe for euer, then to giue them an occaſion to ſtumble, or to be offended, or at the leaſt made weake. Therfore Peter ſemeth not without good cauſe to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; hyde from them his libertie, for whoſe ſakes he diſſembled. But if you will haue reſpect vnto them for whoſe ſakes Paul was zelous &amp; carefull, you will then ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter diſſembled without cauſe, and that he was worthely reprehended of Paul. For he had preached vnto them that by Chriſt alone all men are iuſtifyed: and therfore the
<pb facs="tcp:13129:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ceremonies of the Lawe were not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Which thynge he had confirmed before by his owne example, eatynge indifferently all maner of meates, and that both godly &amp; profitablie. But when for feare of thoſe which came from Hieruſalem, he diſſembled agayne &amp; cloked this libertie, he ſore offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Gentyles, cauſynge them to doute of this doctryne, that by Chriſt only we be iuſtifyed and ſaued: of the Gentyles there were manye, but of thoſe that came from Hieruſalem, there were but fewe. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the offence geuen to the Gentyles, was ſuch as myght haue cauſed them vtterly to fale away from Chriſte: whereas, yf the Iewes had ben offended, it myght perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture haue ben a cauſe only of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, where by ſome emonge them might haue ben weakned, or elles through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of conſcience might then have defiled them ſelues: but yet they ſhould not haue ben ſo cleane alienated from Chriſte, but that ſome of them might haue ben won<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e agayne to ſounde and perfecte faith, when Peter according to that his example which he had before geuen them, ſhould diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ſoberly haue declared vnto them the cauſe of his libertie, as Paul afterwardes dyd. To conclude, ſeyng we ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie
<pb facs="tcp:13129:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſſe forwarde towardes the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and fulnes of fayth, there ſhould more regard haue bene had of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentyles, which were already come to a cleare know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, then of thoſe which as yet dyd ſticke to the ordinances &amp; ceremonyes of the world: which alſo through longe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome &amp; obſeruation might haue bene the more confirmed in theyr errour. This dyd Paul co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder, when he wold not circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Titus: And he reioyceth that he gaue no place to thoſe that contended for that mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, not for an houre. And this dyd he that the veritie of the Goſpell myght continue.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, we muſt conſydre, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be true or falſe brethren, whiche goe about to diminiſhe &amp; impaire the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie: for we muſt haue onlye a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the true brethren. For albeit we ought at all tymes to haue ſuch a conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all men, yea euen of the profeſſed enemyes of the truthe, that we geue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to none to ſpeake euill of our well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doynge, &amp; for that cauſe alſo we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go and forſake euen much of our libertie: yet ought we this alway to do in ſuch ſorte that the truth of the Goſpell be not hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thereby. As for example: If a man would at this daye, for the obſtinate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes
<pb facs="tcp:13129:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Goſpelles ſake (which do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre and blaſpheme all that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from vs,<note place="margin">he applieth this doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to our time &amp; ſtate of religion.</note> ſeyng they abhorre &amp; blaſpheme Chriſt hym ſelfe and his Goſpell) ſtyll diſſemble the libertie of outwarde thynges, whiche the falſe churchmen haue taken from the people of God by ſubtiltye and tyrannye: he in ſo doyng ſhould not only make them nothyng the better, but rather more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them in euill &amp; greatly offende tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe whiche haue receaued Chriſt, whiles he ſhoulde ſtill preache vnto them the naked truth and vtterly voyde of examples.</p>
            <p>For there is no ſmale numbre whiche will hardly be perſwaded, that all thynges are layed vppe for vs in Chriſte alone, when there is ſo much attributed &amp; ſo much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit geuen to mans inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Out of dout there is great faulte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted herin nowe a dayes, not onlye of the common people, but euen of the head &amp; cheif ſtandard bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Goſpell nowe revyuinge and ſpringinge vppe agayn. In dede I confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſo euer hath ben ordeyned againſt the libertie of externall thynges,<note place="margin">Emonges theſe are to be placed cappes, typ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pettes, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſes, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kebreade.</note> as diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of perſons meates, dayes, places, &amp; other like thinges innumerable, hath ben alltogether brought in by the rable of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt yet becauſe the comon people were
<pb facs="tcp:13129:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſuaded that all ſuche thinges were com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes of the Church, ruled and guyded by goddes ſpirite: therfore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued them generally as thynges proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge from godes will and appoyntmente.<note place="margin">Note here why and when we ought to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe our liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie: that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple lacking inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſteme thes ceremonies as thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of God, or elles not.</note> And for this cauſe we muſte euen in theſe oure dayes be circumſpect in vſynge the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie purchaſed for vs by Chriſt, and with Paul ſomtymes circumciſe Timothy: that is to ſay, for oure partes, vſe well ſome ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes which other men abuſe: ſekyng (as it were) an occaſion by that meanes, to preache Chriſt ſyncerely and purely. Albeit thes inuentions of men can by no meanes be compared to circumciſion and ſuch like ordinances of God.</p>
            <p>But what is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon practiſe of men in thes matters: many there be, which fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the ſelaunder of the croſſe, &amp; in vayn ſekinge to pleaſe bothe men and God, yea euen there, where the goſpel hath ben long preached, when nowe wordes and talke requyre examples of workes and deedes,<note place="margin">the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the faint and colde goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers.</note> pretendyng other mens weaknes, wheras they are alltogeather clogged with theyr owne infirmitie: do not only continue ſtill ſlaues them ſelues to mens traditione: but alſo bryng other men in to the like ſlauery and bondage. Oh, ſay they, nothyng is to
<pb facs="tcp:13129:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> be attempted raſſhely: thes thynges haue continued many yeares: they can not be taken awaye ſodenly: We muſt haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the weake. If we ſhould goe haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; raſſhely to worke, we ſhould not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the Goſpel but ouerthrowe it. But thes faynt harted Goſpellers I wolde haue to conſydre what this ſayenge meaneth: The kyngdome of God ſuffereth violence, and the violente take it by force. Math. xj. And moreouer that thes thinges are not raſſhelye or vnadviſedlye attempted, but when they be chaunged wher as Chriſt is not yet preached, and without fayth: but they are not ſo wher Chriſte is alreadye preached, and the nette of the Goſpell hath bene ſo longe caſte forthe, that it hathe in maner taken ſo much as in that countrey or place may be taken, and nowe nothinge remayneth, but to bryng credit to our wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and to confyrme the ſame by examples of doynges. Surelye the caſe ſtandynge thus, ſuche workes alſo as men haue put their confydence in more then in Chriſte, muſt be forſaken, &amp; men muſt conſydre that there can be no fellouſhipp betwene Chriſt and Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>And it is a thynge abſurde and foliſh, to goe about to preſcribe a longe tyme for
<pb facs="tcp:13129:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the receiuyng of the truth, becauſe falſhode and vntruthe hath by litle and litle crepte in, and growne of longe tyme. In dede ſo ſhoulde we haue no more holde of Chriſt then of Antichriſt. Dowtles, yf we receyue hym not as ſone as we know hym, we ſhal neuer enioye hym. Moſes, Samuel, Elias, Ezechias, Ioſias, dealt not in this ſorte,<note place="margin">marke the daunger yf we receaue not Chriſt purely, for ſakinge all Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſo ſone as we know him</note> but ſo ſone as they had reſtored the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lawe to the people, forthwith they abolyſhed all abhominations at once, and reſtored the Ceremonyes of God. Wherefore yt ys to no purpoſe, that they ſay which allwayes bragge that there are greater thynges to be vrged and called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, then the reformation of Ceremonyes: ſo becommynge patrones of Antichriſtes reliques and remnauntes. Ceremonies are the badges or teſtimonyes of religion,<note place="margin">the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are only baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for we ſhold make no de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lay in abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhyng of all other ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies of a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tichriſt</note> and therfore we begyn alſo our Religion with the Ceremonye of Baptiſme. And alſo if any man after he is excommunicated for his wickednes, be receaued agayn through hys repentance, he ys ſtraight reconciled to the Churche by the Sacrament of the lordes ſupper / wherfore they muſt nedes be very weake in the fayth of Chriſt, which prolong and differ the remouynge of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes Ceremonyes: And dowtles it wilbe
<pb facs="tcp:13129:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> longe ere newnes of life appeare in thoſe men yf euer it appeare at all. In dede, we ſee at this day cold and ſlacke procedinges in Chriſtian profeſſion in thoſe places wher Antichriſtes Ceremonyes are borne with all,<note place="margin">The cauſe why anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes remayne vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> and ſuffered to continue, and all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges much more lyuely and effectuall where they be aboliſhed. For if they ſtay and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne any tyme vnreformed, there can be no other cauſe therof but that eyther the worde of God is not thoroughly receaued or not eſtemed and regarded accordingly. For howe ſo euer thoſe that ſuppoſe them ſelues to be ſtronge in the fayth, will excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe them ſelues that they vſe not thes thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: where is yet, I praye you, their zeale for Chriſtes glorie, or theyr care for theyr brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which as they yet ſtill vſe them ſo (no doubt) they do it of weaknes of faith. Vndowtedly as there is no agremente at all betwene Chriſt and Beliall, ſo ſyncere &amp; vnfayned Chriſtians can by no meanes ſuffer them ſelues to be clogged with any whitt of Antichriſtes traſhe and trumpery yea and withall they will endeuour ſo to purge the Churche therof as the glorie of God may chefly be therby aduaunced. And further, they will haue ſuch regarde of the weaker ſorte that they will do nothyng
<pb facs="tcp:13129:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnaduyſedlye or oute of ſeaſon, but will teache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weake with all gentlenes to waxe ſtronger in knowleadge, &amp; labor with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples alſo to bringe them forwarde, not regardinge the blyndnes of a feawe who are to much addycted to Antichriſtes Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes, &amp; perhappes no true nor fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren, whereby they myght in the meane tyme offende manye other weake ones, who continuallye thynke thus with them ſelues: If thes thynges were ſo euill as they are taken to be, they ſhold ſurelye be aboliſhed. And agayn, if the other were ſo good, all men, eſpecially ſuche as recken them ſelues Chriſtians, would in deede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and embrace them. Thes men ſurely, if they be electe, ſhall at the lengthe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, althoughe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world offend them, and no man edifye them: but in the meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, woo be vnto them by whom they are offended. Wherfore as ſone as true godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and the righte worſhipp of God hath ben preached and profeſſed of manye, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtes Ceremonyes and rites ought by and by to be abrogated, and the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herof may not be prolonged &amp; delayed vntill godlynes be in all poyntes growne to perfection: for elles ſhoulde they neuer be aboliſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Theſe are in dede ouer mylde and toetoe ſofte and ſobre Chriſtians, which can beare with all ſuche Antichriſtian traſſhe: lyke vnto them who at Corinth knowyng that an Idol was nothynge, dyd eate thynges offered to Idoles, and boſted (as thes oure men do) in this wiſe: In outwarde mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters we are free: what is that to me that an other vſeth thoſe thynges nowghtely? I wyll vſe them well. For as theſe men weakened the fayth of many both in that throughe theyr example they dyd the leſſe abhorre Idoles, &amp; alſo in that for the moſte parte, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated with them againſt theyr conſciences: ſo (no doubte) do thes our luke warme and mylke ſoppe Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers nowe a dayes. They knowe right well that Antichriſtes Ceremonyes, that is to ſay, all ſuche as haue ben brought in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Godes worde, are not worth a ruſſhe. And becauſe they are outwarde thynges, wherin we haue fredome, they wil vſe them frelye, not conſyderinge that manye thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are laufull which are not expedient, &amp; that our libertie ought to be employed to the commoditie of other, whom they in the meane tyme offende and obſcure the glorie of Chriſte: for they confirme them in theyr errour, which as yet knowe not that theſe
<pb facs="tcp:13129:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> thynges are free and at libertie. As for the patrones therof, the profeſſed enemyes of Chriſte, they cauſe them to reioyce and ſett them a gogge. And finally they weake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith of the feble which had forſaken them and caſt them awaye. Thus do they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth prouyde goodlye for the weake ones, yea they ſerue rather theyr owne belies, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng to gratifye ſuch as eyther are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes enemyes or elles backeſlyders.<note place="margin">Marke what they be that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious ceremonies</note> For no man beſydes theſe will earneſtly contende for ſuperſtytious Ceremonyes. This is theyr modeſt bearyng and delayenge, wher with they are ſo farre from furtherynge of the Goſpell, that by litle and litle they do vtterly aboliſhe it. Surely we may thanke thes men,<note place="margin">Marke the cauſe why the Goſpel goeth not foreward: God will haue no fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhipp with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall.</note> that at this daye all thynges are turned vpſyde downe in many places wher the Goſpell hath ben longe tyme preached: where as we haue neuer yet ſene the lyke come to paſſe, where, at the earneſte &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere preachinge of Chriſte, Ceremonyes haue alſo ben reformed, accordinge to the rule of his word.</p>
            <p>For as muche therfore as Chriſt ſo ſore deteſteth offences, and crieth woe vnto the wordle becauſe of offences: woo vnto the man by whom offence commeth: we muſte with all diligence, take heede both in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:13129:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> thynges and in all other, that we be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to no man, but eſpecially the litle ones: I meane not in age only, but in fayth and vnderſtandinge alſo. The perfecte know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and of Chriſt, is lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge. What ſo euer therfore may eyther hynder or obſcure it by anye meanes, let it neither be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor don<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of vs. But let vs remoue all ſuche thynges to the vttermoſt of oure powers. And let vs prouoke them both by exhortations and examples, that they expreſſe and declare thoſe thynges in theyr lyfe, geuinge no place herin either to theyr owne affections or other mens, ſeynge that it ys better to be drowned in the ſea then to geue offence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Obiections and Anſweares concernynge apparell of Preſtes and Mynyſters.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ An obiection.</head>
               <p>THIS apparell was vſed in Kynge Edwardes dayes of Godly men, as Crammer, Rydley, &amp; ſuche like, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for nowe Godly men ought not to refuſe yt: althoughe alſo the Papiſtes beyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlye men euer abuſed yt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Anſweare.</head>
               <p>¶ The manner of the faſte, which Iohns dyſcyples vſed being good, was not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for alſo exacted of Chriſtes dyſcyples: but rather for that yt was an obſeruacion of manes deuyſe corruptly abuſed of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſies, no more mete for the ſyncerytye of the Goſpel, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> old barrels for newe wyne, or newe clothe for an old garment, ſo nowe the fillinge and clowtinge vp of old Popi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe apparell, with the newe purenes of the
<pb facs="tcp:13129:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Goſpell, muſt yether cauſe corruptione to burſt and loſe bothe, or els make the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of the newe from the old worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Obiection,</head>
               <p>¶ Seing ſom men which be nowe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, dyd in Kynge Edwardes dayes vſe this apparell with feruent zeale and good conſcience, the ſame nowe refuſynge yt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not to be moued with zeale and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but of deſyre of novelties and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Anſweare.</head>
               <p>¶ Paule did fearve God in feruent zeale &amp; good and pure conſcience euen from his progenytors, yet comynge to more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, did fynde &amp; confes thes thinges to be hurtfull and vyle, whiche he had eſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and vſed as profytable, and albeyt he had circumcyſed Tymothe, yet wold he not ſuffre Tytus to be cyrcumcyſed: ſo ſome ſuche as proceade in knowleadge and expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryence dothe fynde this apparrell vyle and hurtfull, which befor they thowght profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and not hurtfull. And albeit that cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie dyd moue them to beare with the wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, as it did Paul in circumcyſynge Tymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, yet faythefullnes to keape the truthe of the Goſſpell, wher yt hathe bene longe preached, cawſythe thoſe ſame Preachers
<pb facs="tcp:13129:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> not to yealde or ſhrynke for anye force or portunytie, as Paul not circumcyſyng Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, not of ſyngularitie and deſyre of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, but of faythfullnes, zeale, and good conſcyence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Obiection.</head>
               <p>¶ Becauſe all Byſhoppes in Ingland, and manye other good Preachers, which had once refuſed this apparell yet nowe by occaſione haue receauid yt agayne, and but fewe ther be that ſtill yet refuſe yt, therfor yt ſemeth more expedient, and les domage of offence and dyſagrement in the churche to bringe fewe in ſmale eſtymacion to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formytie with the Byſhopes, &amp; theyr mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude muche eſtemed: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther to reduce the Byſhoppes to other inferiors, or ſuffre inferiors to dyffre in thoſe thinges from them being Byſhoppes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Anſweare.</head>
               <p>¶ When as Paul and Peter being at Antioche did bothe eate meate wyth the Gentylls, and at the comyng of certayne from Iames, Peter fearinge them of the cyrcumcyſion withdrewe &amp; ſeperated hym ſealfe, ſo as other Iewes then with Barna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bas weare browght in to that Ipocryſie &amp; diſſymulation: then Paul openly withſtode Peter as worthie of reprofe by ſuche dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge,
<pb facs="tcp:13129:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> compellinge the gentills to Iewiſhe obſervacions, and ſo not rightlye proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truthe of the Goſpell. Therfor yf right procedinge to the truthe of the Goſpell, haue once made bothe theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to agree, leauinge of Popyſhe appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, as Paul and Peter in leauinge of the Iewiſhe rites, and the feare and reſpecte of ſome perſonnes moue nowe the one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as Peter was moued to ſhrinke to reic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rytes agayne in ſuche a caſe: the moſt expedient waye to auoyde danger of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and dyſagrement in the church, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute regard of perſonages, feare, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of men, to keape and mayntayne the truthe of the Goſpell with ſynceritie, and lybertie vnſeparable from the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Obiection.</head>
               <p>¶ Chriſtyan obedyence requyreth obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of all thinges indifferent, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by auctoritye: apparell is indifferentt nowe in Ingland, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by auctoritie: therfor chriſtiane obedyence requyreth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion of yt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſweare.</head>
               <p>¶ Waſhinge of handes before meates amonge the Iewes, was a thinge as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent of yt felfe as this apparell, &amp; not ſo moche abuſed of the Pharyſies as this of
<pb facs="tcp:13129:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the papiſtes, and beynge commaunded and vrged by them that had auctoritie, Chriſt teachinge true Chriſtian obedience, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith not the obſeruinge of it, and chargyth ſuche as do obſerue and vrge it, with brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of Godes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandementes for their owne traditions, ypocriſie, and blynd lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the blynd, and ſo concludeth as euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlye maye appeare, that the obedience and auctoritie of Chriſtians conſyſteth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in commandinge nor obſervinge, but rather rotyng vp all ſuch plants not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his heauenly father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Obiection.</head>
               <p>¶ Yf the Prince maye therto be perſuaded all Byſhoppes ſeame that they wolde be glade to aboliſh thes garmentes of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe blaſſphemous and ydolatrous preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hodes, but yf the Prince will force all My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to receaue and retayne them, or els putt them out of theyr lyvinges and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, then yt ſeameth better to keape lyvinges, libertie of ſyncere doctrine with this apparrell, then without yt to loſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge, keape ſylence and leaue the churche deſtytute of ſo manye good preachars, yea &amp; ſo offend a godlye Prince, by whom God hathe gracyouſlie reſtored the prechars &amp; preachinge of Chriſtes Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13129:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Anſweare.</head>
               <p>¶ If all Byſhoppes and Preachers reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectinge God, &amp; the cauſe only haue wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed and perſuaded not to vſe this apparell, as Ioab not to nombre the people, and yet reſpectinge the Prynces commandemente contrarye to theyr formall wyſhinge and perſuadynge ſhuld yelde in dedes as Ioab did. Then weare to be feared ſuche ſequell of plagues on the people with great greife to the Prynce, nowe heare as was then there: and as the Iſmalites deſtroinge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of the Ammorytes accordinge to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des commandementt, yet leauing ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyques of the ſame by theyre owne negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or affection, or pollycie, weare conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually corrupted, polluted, &amp; plagued with the Ammorytes, ſo is it to be feared in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, that the abolyſhinge of muche Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtrye accordinge to Godes will reueled by his worde, and by reſeruinge of ſome reliques of the ſame by humayn negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, affectione, and pollycie, ſhold cauſe this realme contynually to be polluted, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and plagued with Papiſtrie: thes thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered moue many good prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars to be conſtantt, zealous, and ſyncere, as in will and doctrine, ſo in conuerſacion and manners, reprouyng and refuſinge all
<pb facs="tcp:13129:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> thinges propre &amp; belonginge to Papiſtrie: eſpeciallie to the Idolatrous blaſhphemous and traiterous preſthoode, moſte peſtilent enemye to all Chriſtyane auctoritye, and princelie dignitie, and therfor manye good preachers the rather dyſpoſed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of the Prynce &amp; the people, loſinge lyuinge, lyfe to confyrme theyre doctryne preached, then keapinge liuinges with flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, with danger of the Prynce, &amp; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to buyld &amp; bringe agayn, that which by faythfull preachinge hathe bene deſtroyed, reprouid &amp; refuſyd, ſo ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ſuch preachers be put to ſylence, theyr dedes declaringe &amp; confyrminge theyr doctryne: nor ſuche be thought to be left deſtytute of thoſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, by whoſe doctryne &amp; manners alſo the church is taught as to knowe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace true doctryne, &amp; ſyncere rites &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; ſo ſhall Godly &amp; faythfull doctryne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed with lyke dedes, by Godes grace gyue no offence, butt vnfayned thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to a godly Prynce reſtoringe &amp; recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing true doctryne with ſyncere rites and manners to Godes glory, to the Prynces honor, &amp; the people edyfycation thorowgh Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>¶ It is good for a man to be feruent in good thinges. <bibl>Galat. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A prayer mete &amp; neceſſarye for oure tyme and all tymes to be vſed.</head>
            <p>OH Lord God maker of all thinges, thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art fearful &amp; glorious, thou righteous &amp; marcyful. Thou which onely art moſt gracious, onely liberal, onely iuſt, almighty &amp; euerlaſtinge: thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of thyn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomid &amp; riche mercyes deliuerydſt thyn electe and choſen from all trouble, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaffe for thy Sonnes ſake to delyuer, and preſerue vs from all euill, and alſo from doynge of thoſe thynges, whiche thou in thy holye word haſt forbidden. Oh be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious vnto vs, and thinck vpon thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante made with oure forfathers of olde, as Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob, thy true, and faythfull ſeruauntes. And geue vs all ſuche hartes, that we may vnfaynedly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, and ſerue the by true obedience to thy holye Lawes, and Commaundementes. Send vs inwarde peace in conſcience, that we maye be at one with the, ſo that thou neuer forſake vs in the tyme of trouble: be vnto vs in all oure nede and neceſſytye as a ſuer rock, defence, buckler and ſhyeld, that vnder the winges of thy deuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye
<pb facs="tcp:13129:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> we maye be ſaffly kepte, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd, that Sathan and his wicked imppes neuer preuayle agaynſt vs, by anye cruell tyranny, or oppreſſion. But graunt (good Lorde) for thyne owne glories ſake, yea for thy Sonn Chriſte Ieſus ſake, that we in the tyme of tryall maye ſhewe oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as valiaunt warriours firmlye &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to fyght vnder thy banner, and not lyke cowardes at euery blaſt of winde, be redy to rune away, ſtarting back, and ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the felowſhip of Godes ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Thincking here in this wicked world for a longe tyme to enioye the riches and pleaſures therof, the whiche tyme yf we conſyder is but as one drop of rayne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parid to the hole ſea, yea yf for this ſhort and momentanie tyme we might gete the hole worlde, and looſe oure owne ſoules, what ſhuld it profit? or what is there (oh Lorde) to redeme our ſoules agayne with all: In euery ſouldyer that in this world takethe in hand vnder his Capitayne to fight, there is requyred in hym, that he be ſtoute, valiaunt and manly, that when the pinche of the battayle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mith, he may then ſurely ſtand and fighte in hope of victory. Euen ſo lyke wyſe (oh good Lord) it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of euery one of vs, whiche profeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13129:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> thy holy ghoſpell, that we ſhew our ſelues manfullye to fyght for the defence of the ſame, that when the brunt of perſecution by Godes prouidence to vs is myniſtred, we may then ſhew our ſelues as true and faythfull Chriſtyans, to fyght that good fyght for an eternall tryumphe &amp; victory, in geuing &amp; offring vp oure owne bodies, for a ſacryfice vnto the Lord our God, who is euer ready to ſtrenghthen them that put theyr full truſt in hym. Oh good Lorde, graunt for thy names ſake vnto vs ſuche plentie of thy grace, that when time requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe, as we do beleue in hart to iuſtyfica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo by mouthe we may make true confeſſion to ſaluation, that the frute of the ſame may be to vs in the latter daye, ioye, comfort, and eternall conſolation, thorough Ieſus Chriſt, by whoſe deathe &amp; merytes we are made inheretours of hys euerlaſtinge kingdome. To whome with the Father, Sonne and Holye Ghooſt be prayſe glory and dominion world without ende. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OH Lord deſtroy all the workes of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: confort thyne that are in adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytie: helpe thoſe that be in troble for thy names ſake, haue mercy vpon vs, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs thy true faithfull obedient &amp; thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſernaunts, Lorde inclyne oure hartes into thy teſtimonies, and not into any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful luſte. Oh turne away oure eyes, that they behold not vanytie, but quycken thou vs in thy lawe: beſtowe vpon vs thy worde (oh Lord) ſo that we never abuſe it, neither turne it vnto wantonnes, but that entering into the grace of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce we may therein increaſe, and therein contynew, and that tyll oure lyues end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>TO my faythfull Brethren, we geue thankes to God for your conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and vpryght delynge in this gret controuerſie now rayſyd by packynge of enemys about the wearinge of popiſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and as ye haue well begonne, ther is no doubt, but the Lorde in mercy ſhall kepe ye pure and blameles to the ende. It hathe byne no ſmall ioye and comfort to many godlye and good Churches, which dayly and howerly prayeth for your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and that it wolde pleaſe God to eaſe it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his good will and pleaſure is. So on the other ſyde muche lamentynge the blyndnes of thoſe that goeth about to defende it: but eſpeciallye thoſe that are become perſecutors of their godly &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren: but as charite requireth we deſyre God neuer laye it to theyr charge, but geue them grace to ryſe agayne vnto whom we leue them wether they ſtande or falle. Let Lottes wyfe be a warnynge in tyme to take hede. Moſes that bleſſyd ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uant of God wolde not alter the valew of a curten, or a lytill pyne in the Arcke, ſo ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous was he in the Lordes worke: nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brought any thynge out of his owne heade to the people: But had always the
<pb facs="tcp:13129:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> warrant of the worde for hym, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, what ſo euer may be obiected agaynſt the refuſars of thoſe ydolators garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, for what ſo euer they brynge, may be reduſed into this poyntes, that Godly men ether nede not or ought not to be ſcrupulous in ſo ſmall a matter, which anſwer ye ſhall vnderſtand as folowith with an anſwere to a queſtion at the end hereof. The Lord for his Chriſt ſake make Ephrahim and Manaſſis agre, that we maye all with on hart and mynde vnfaynydly ſeke Godes glorye, the edificacion of his people, that we may lyue in all godly peace, vnyte, and concord. This grant, o Lorde, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whom, with the, and the Holy goſte, be all prayſe, glory, and honor for euer and euer. Fare ye well deare Brethren.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DEarly belouyd, you that haue wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, vnderſtanding, and wyll to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructyd in this controuerſie now rayſyd in the Churche about apparell, at thys tyme thys ſhall ſuffyce. Yt is true that the teachers of handye craftes affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that no man can attayne to ſuche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente perfeccyon in worke, as maye be diſputed of by reaſone, muche leſſe when the rule of religion muſte be framyd accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to the rule of Godes wyll, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of all perfeccyon, may we loke that any thyng can ſo perfectly be performyd of vnperfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that in all poynts yt may anſwere to the perfeccion that God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith: neuertheles God requirith his ſeruice to be ſuche as hym ſealfe is, deuyne, pure, ſyncere, vnmingled, and in no parte corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptyd, and as lacke of ſtrenthe ſhal not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs, in that we can not, ſo neclygence makythe vs more wickyd, yf that we may performe, and we will not. Fyrſte we are requityd to loue God with all our hartes, all our myndes, and all our ſtrength, that preciſenes is comendable, which withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith not a lytill, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all is requiryd. Thou ſhalt be perfect with thy Lorde thy god.<note place="margin">Deut. 18.</note> Thou ſhalt not bende ether to thy ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande, or to the leafte. Thou ſhalt nether
<pb facs="tcp:13129:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> adde, nether diminiſhe of that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundyd. Thou ſhalt not inquier for the gods of the Gentyls, ſayinge: Howe dyd thoſe Gentyles ſerue theyr godes. Thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lorde thy god. For whatſoeuer the Lorde abhorreth, that dyd they to theyr godes. God wyll haue his children ſo to abhorre theſe ſuperſticion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld fle euen from that infeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that comythe by hearynge.<note place="margin">The zeall that God requirith.</note> Furthermore, ſo many thinges as ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyd of leprous, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtreous, dead bodys, were many, which myght not be touchyd without defyling, what other thinges were they in that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de people,<note place="margin">God kepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all outwarde ſhew of Popery.</note> but exerciſes of precyſe purenes and cleanes, the obſeruance of ſuche ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, althoughe it hath byn longe ſynce abolyſhyd, yet the euerlaſtinge truthe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynyth: muche more in preſence of the bodye, that no prophane or defylyd thinge may be minglyd with gods ſeruice. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer god forbydyth all ſtrange corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious mixtures, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he forbyddyth them to ſowe land with diuers ſeedes, to plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe with an oxe and an aſſe, to weare ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyne and wollen to gether. For lyberte &amp; coſtome euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſte matters bredythe boldnes, &amp; in hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement god hath alſo reſpecte to the kynde of apparell. Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie
<pb facs="tcp:13129:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> when this cleanes is ſtreachyd euen to brute beaſtes,<note place="margin">marke well.</note> who wold not beleue that God requirith an vtter deteſtacion of all vncleanes, eſpecially in religion. Seing all theſe lawes perteyne to the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, accordinge to the ſame preciſe rule dyd the holy fathers exerciſe them ſelues vnto puryte, therfore it is neuer rede that the godly Patriarches dyd ſacrifyce vpon the Idolators alters, but whytherſoeuer they remouid,<note place="margin">Example of holy men.</note> always they buyldid newe alters. Furthermore Abraham wolde not take a thryde of the Kynge of Sodoma. Iacob buryed the earinges that weare or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes of ſuperſticion, with the Idoles them ſelues. Moyſes to blemiſhe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God wolde accepte no condicions at all, there ſhall not remayne on houſe, ſaythe he very preciſlye. Dauith wold not take the names of the Idoles in his lypes. Ezechias brake the braſen ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not only cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyd the vſe of it.<note place="margin">What gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heryty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther be, then the Papiſtes?</note> The Holy ghoſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſithe thoſe godly Kinges, which deſtroyed the highe places, as Ezechias and Ioſias, in whiche places ſomtyme the people dyd worſhip god. Elyazer wold not fayne that he dyd eate ſwynes fleſhe. S. Pawle byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dythe, Refrayne from all ſhew of euyll. S. Iohn forbyddyth vs to ſalute an hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke.
<pb facs="tcp:13129:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> And Polycarpus his diſciple, as I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneus wytneſſith, when he mett an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke, wolde not gyue hym other anſwere, but that he knewe hym to be the Deuells eldeſte ſonne. for ſuche feare had the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels &amp; theyr diſciples, that they wolde not comunicate withe on worde with any that had corruptyd the faith. Fynallie S. Pawle in playne wordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſnes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> ſayinge, Take hede that ye walke preciſlye or exactlye, for ſo the greke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſignifieth. Laſt of all, let vs not forget what our Sauiour Chriſt ſaythe: He that is faythfull in the leaſte, wyl be faythfull in the moſte. Who alſo teachith vs, howe faythfully and preciſlye we ſhulde walke, what colde be more preciſly ſpoken of, the law ſhall paſſe vntyll all be fullfyllyd, and he that breakyth one of the leaſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements, and teachith other ſo to do, ether by worde, or by example, ſhalbe leaſt in the Kyngdome of heauen. Yt is euident by theſe reaſons and examples, that no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſenes or ſcrupuloſite in godes religion, can be to muche or blame worthie. Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance, ther is no controuerſy, but yt is lawfull as the good creature of god, and to this purpoſe pertayne thoſe ſayinges: The kyngdome of heauen is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13129:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> meate nor drynke. Meate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendith vs not to god. Whatſoeuer enterithe in to the mouth, defylyth not the man. All thinges ar cleane to them that ar cleane. &amp; other lyke places of ſcripture, all which they pertayne to the matter or creature &amp; ſubſtance only, not to euery vſe, faſſion, or maner of vſynge. It is to muche doltyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not to vnderſtand all thynge a ryght, excepte we wyll alſo conclude of the ſame places, that by glotony, dronkenes, whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſquiſyd aparell, and ſuche lyke, the lawe of god is not broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. garments ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ar vrgyd in reſpecte of the forme and vſe, they are not indifferent, and fyrſt of the ende, which they labor ſo muche to proue that it is chaungyd, that thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which before were vſyd to ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, now are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyd for order &amp; comlynes. No godly man doubtyth, but the Quenes Maieſte intendinge an other end in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of thoſe thinges, then the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes vſyd them for. But who ſo well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of thoſe thinges, ſhall play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely ſe, that the end which thé commander propoundyth, dothe not folowe, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the diuerſite of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſe them, and them that iudge of them, a cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary end enſuythe, for many popiſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:13129:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> vſe them to the ſame ſuperſticious end that they dyd in Popery, and greateſt of all is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of ignorant people, that iudgith none otherwyſe of them.<note place="margin">Cor. 8.</note> All men haue not knowledge, for ſome with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Idole, euen yet do eate meate offred to Idoles. So Gedeon made an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phode,<note place="margin">Iud. 8.</note> not that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſhulde go a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge after it, yet was it the deſtruction of hym and his howſe foreuer. Secondly it can not ſerue for order and comlynes,<note place="margin">Cor. 14.</note> which hath in it no neceſſary cauſe of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. Let all thinges be donne for edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Nether can it be conuertyd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes of the Chriſtian Churche, which is the chaſte ſpowſe of Chriſt, which is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Antichriſt, and the fylthye whore of Babylon. What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent hath Chriſt with Belyall? what porcion hath the faythfull with the infydell? or what agrement hath the temple of God with Images? Yf the reaſon of S. Paule be examynyd,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> by the which he diſſuadith the Corynthians fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eating of meate offeryd to Idoles, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me may be alſo extendyd to garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratyd to Idolatry. The nature of cery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and rytes is to make the vſer to haue felowſhip with the principall of that religion, as the Iewes of the alter, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb facs="tcp:13129:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> with Chriſt, and Gentils with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells. As manye as are partakers of the breade which we breake, are partakers of the bodye of Chriſte. They therfore that eate meate offeryd to Idoles, are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of deuells. And as many as are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized haue put on Chriſt: it is not to be fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryd, leaſte as many as weare antychriſtes robes, wil take more yf auctorite comand it, neyther dothe the auctoryte of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrat excuſe vs, except we thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, that Sergius Paulus myght permyte that S. Paule had forbydden the ſentence of Iamys, which is,<note place="margin">Act. 15. Deut. 12.</note> that the gentyls ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de abſtayne from the polucion of Idoles, God will borowe nothynge of Idoles to garnyſh or become his religion. thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lorde thy god, but rather he commandyth vtterly to deſtroye theyr alters, woddes, pyllers, and theyr very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. He forbyddyth them alſo to brynge any thinge in to theyr howſes that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gythe to Idoles. Eſaye chap. 30. byddyth thoſe that are earneſtly turnyd to the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippe of god, to caſt awaye the reliques of Idolatrie, You ſhall, ſayth he, put out the couerynge of the Imagis of ſyluer,<note place="margin">that is all thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Idolatry.</note> &amp; the precious veſtyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, and thou ſhalt caſte them awaye lyke
<pb facs="tcp:13129:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> a menſtrous clowte, and ſaye vnto yt: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nawnte, or get the hence. Fynallye when all godly men abhorre the monſtrous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell of Fryers, Monkes, Chanons, I can not ſe, by what order they ſhulde exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the ornaments of Popiſhe Preaſtes, whoſe order is as wyckyd as Freyers, Monkes, or any other, which thyng may be ſayd of the reſte of the Popiſhe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies, which may all with lyke precepte and coloure, &amp; by as good reaſon be receuid in the Churches as thoſe. But admyttinge that theſe thynges were neuer ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, yet it can not be that we ſhulde thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them lawfull, for vs to vſe them: for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thinges, which by them ſealues are lawfull, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other circumſtance is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd to them, then become they vnlawfull for a Chriſtian to vſe them, as in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Firſt we can not caſt of all doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hauing ſo many reaſons on our ſyde, and ſo manye examples bothe of learnyd men, and beſt reformyd Churches, but in all thinges moſt indifferent. Saint Paule chargith euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be certanly perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd in his owne mynde, which ſome men vntruly tranſlate, Let euery man abownde in his owne ſence, for he that with doubt of conſcience eatyth, which of it ſealfe is
<pb facs="tcp:13129:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> lawfull, is condemnyd, becauſe he doth it not of fayth. Now the aſſurance of fayth muſte be ſought no where, but in Gods worde. Secondlye, thowghe we ſhulde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfye our conſciences, yet this man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylid, which is not perſuadid by Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, but encreaſed by our examples, that he dare do that, whereof before he doubted, and this is to geue an offence, as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call it to anger them, for they that are beſt pleaſyd with theſe matters, are moſt offendyd, that they ſtomble and falle, we muſt not do what ſo euer is lawfull, but what ſo euer alſo is profytable to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying: nether muſt we only regarde what lyberte permyttyth, but rather what our brothers proffyt requiryth. Thyrdlye, we maye not altogether neclecte what infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells iudge of vs in the vſynge of thinges lawfull by them ſealfes, and therefore S. Paule byddeth them that are callyd to the feaſtes of the gentyls, ſo ſone as mencyon is made of meate offeryd to Idoles, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from eatinge of it, becauſe of hym that tolde of it, and his conſcience, not of hym ſealfe, but of an other. What the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes iudge of vs, maye eaſely be ſeene by this, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harding for the retayning of thoſe Popiſhe cerymonies, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teynith hope that
<pb facs="tcp:13129:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> popery ſhalbe reſtoryd: what the ignorant people iudge of the reamnants of papiſtri retaynyd, wyſe men may well conſyder. Herunto might haue byne ioynid the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of olde Doctors, Iuſtinus, Ireneus, Tertullianus, Aguſtyne, Ambros, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtums, Celeſtinus, &amp; almoſt all the reſt, for abhorrynge the cuſtomes and ryghtes of the Iewes and gentyles and heritykes, but Gods truthe nedyth not mans aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, except they that be againſt vs, in this cauſe wyll appeale to the fathers, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall they perceyue, that in nomber both of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and ſentences, we ſhall be nothinge inferior to them. In the meane tyme this maye ſuffyce, to ſhew fyrſt that the precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians is blameles, ſecondly the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ar not indifferent, &amp; thyrdly that thowghe they were indifferent, yet ther is ſufficient reaſon at this tyme, why we ſhoulde not weare them. Come Lord Ieſus, and make an ende of thys wyckyd wordle, that thy ſainctes may come to gether, that we may ſynge with the in thy holy hyll for euer. He that ouercomith, ſhalbe crownyd. Pray, pray, as the Apoſtell Peter ſayth: the end of all thinges is at hand.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ An Anſwere to a queſtion, that was mouyd, whi the godly men wold not weare a ſurples.</head>
            <p>ALthoughe we muſte nedes confeſſe,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwere.</note> that we haue to much conſentyd he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retofore with the Papiſte in robbing and bereuinge God of his glory &amp; honor, yet may we not now in the lyght of Gods truthe contynew a partaker with you in the adulteracion of Chriſtes ſacramentes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our conſciences &amp; knowledge, wherein we iudge our ſealues onlye, not preiudiſynge other mens doinge, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we leaue to God, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ether ſtand or falle. For oure partes we muſt render accompte, not obſtinatly bent againſt any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe approuyd by Gods worde.</p>
            <p>We are perſuadyd,<note place="margin">Maior.</note> that we may not vſe any thinge repugnant to Chriſtian lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, nor mayntayne an opinion of holynes wher none is, whiche were Ipocriſy, nor conſent to Idolatri, which were denyall of the truthe, or diſcorage the godly, incora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge the wyckyd, nor diſtroying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Chriſt, which are bownde to edifye, nor conſent vnto confuſion, wher God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiryth order, nor ſhew diſobedience, wher God requiryth to obeye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Minor.</note>But in vſynge of a ſurples, we ſhulde do that which is repugnaunt to Chriſtian lybertie, maintaine an opinion of holines, where none is, ſhew conſent to Idolatry, deny the truthe, dyſcorage the godly, and incorage the wyckyd or vngodly, conſent to confuſion and ſhew diſobedience, wher God commandithe to obeye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion</note>We may not with good conſcience, as we are perſuadyd weare a ſurples.</p>
            <p>The Maior is prouyd by Saynt Paule Gal. 5. who commandyth to Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, by the example of Chriſt Matt. 15. who wold not haue his diſciples to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne an opinion of holynes,<note place="margin">note the example of good men.</note> whiche the Iewes had in waſſhyng of handes: by the doctryne of Pawle. 2. Cor. 6. who wyll haue no agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the temple of God and the Idoles: by the example of Dany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. 6. who openid his wyndowe towardes Ieruſalem, leſt he myght ſeame to denye his profeſſion or conſent with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyckyd: by the example of Paule Gal. 2. who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouyd Peter for the diſcoragyng of the godly gentiles, and incoraging of the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Iewes: by the doctryne of the ſame Apoſtell. 2. Cor. 13. where he teachith that Mynyſters haue power to edifye, not to deſtroye: by the example of Patriarkes,
<pb facs="tcp:13129:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Prophetes, which in the worſhipping of God, wear by no meanes confowndyd withe the Idolators: by the doctryne of Peter and Iohn actes, which affyrmithe to be more ryght to obey God, then men. But for more euident profe herof, we may let you ſe ſome practiſes of auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Tertulian in his boke De corona militis, lykythe them vnto dom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Idolls, ſuche as do vſe any thinge accordynge to the ornament of Idolles: and further, yf to leane apon an Idoll, is ſtrange from the fayth,<note place="margin">faſtyng is good, yet the godly wold not vſe it that day, as the herytyk dyd.</note> what ſhall ſeame apon the habyte of an Idoll. Auguſtyne ad Caſulanum, warnythe not to faſte on the Sondaye, leaſt therby conſente might be ſhewyd to the wyckyd Maniches. They that weare any thinge after the maner of Idoles, and yf it be ſtrange from fayth to leane apon an Idoll, what is it to weare the habyt of an Idoll. The fourth Counſell of Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Canon. 5. for auoydynge of conſent with Herytyckes, decreed that once dyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge ſhulde be vſyd in Baptyſme. A Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſt of our tyme affyrmith that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels to auoyde conſent to Iudaiſme, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhed the Sabothe daye, and ſanctyfyed the daye of the Lorde. The great Clarke Orygen, as Epiphanius wrytith in his. 2.
<pb facs="tcp:13129:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> boke.<note place="margin">Beware of decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng.</note> 1. Tome, caryed palme withe thos that offeryd to the Image Serapis, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe he proteſtyd openly, that he dyd offer vnto Chriſt, and not vnto Serapis, yet was he excomunycatyd, and caſt out of the Church by the Marters and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors whiche then were at Athens. The Chriſtian ſowdiars which by Iulian ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telte were browght to offer incens,<note place="margin">Beware of deceyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſes.</note> as it is wryten Hiſtoria Tripartita lib. 6. chap. 30. when they perceuyd theyr faute, whiche vnwares they had commytted in conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to Idolatri, they rane forthe into the ſtreats profeſſede theyr relygion, teſtifyed them ſealues to be Chriſtians, affyrmyng that theyr handes only had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentyd vnto Paganiſme,<note place="margin">the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of true Chriſtian.</note> and that theyr hartes dyd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng agre thervnto, and whereas theyr handes had offendyd vnadvyſydlye, they wyſhyd to beſtowe theyr whole bodyes to be tormentyd for Chriſt, althoughe wyth tormentes and paynes moſte creuell and horyble. I truſt we nede not to laboure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further for the profe. By the vſe of the ſurples men are iniciat in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, as it aperith by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pontifycall, De cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico faciendo. Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Galathians by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion rather loſte theyr lyberte in Chriſt, then profytyd any thynge, by iniciatinge
<pb facs="tcp:13129:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> them ſealues in to Iudaiſme. How maye you retayne the lyberte in Chriſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt in his religion by wearinge the Popes lyuerye, we can not perceaue? But by the vſe of the ſurples, is mayntaynyd an Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critycall opinion of holynes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pontificall termithe it Habitum ſancte religionis, the habyt of an holy religion. Durand lib. 3. De rationale diuinorum, ſaythe, That it is Veſtis linea, the lyuyne garment, in which they that ſerue about the ſeruices of the alter and holy thinges, ought to vſe apon theyr clothes, a ſurples, it is for the whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, or it ſignifieth the puryte or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtete, accordinge to that ſayinge: Let your garments, that is, your workes, be white at all tymes, that is cleane:<note place="margin">Marke what ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignes is in the ſurples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentyd by Papiſtes.</note> but for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, it figurith the mortificacion of the fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe. It is callyd a Surples, becauſe that in the olde tyme they dyd weare it apon ſkynny coates, made of the ſkynnes of the deade, whiche is vſyd to this daye in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Churches, repreſentynge that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, after he had ſynnyd,<note place="margin">with what good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can the godly weare yt, iudge good Brother.</note> was clothed with ſuche garments. Thyrdly, it notith Innocenci, and therfore it is put on before all other holye veſtures, becauſe that they that are deputyd to worſhippynge, ought to excell in lyfe and in all vertues, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb facs="tcp:13129:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the ſayinge of the pſalme: Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies do ryghtly cleue vnto me. Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, for the bredthe of it, it betokenythe Charite, wherefore they are worne apon prophane and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon veſtures, it is to be markyd that charite coueryth the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſynnes. Fyftlye, for the faſſyon of it, in that is it made lyke a Croſſe, or Iewes gallows, it fygurythe the paſſion of the Lord, and they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> weare, that ought to be crewcyfyed with the vices and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences. In mayntayninge this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of holynes, with all other inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions, which by lyinge ſeignes, which they haue had to it, we knowe not howe to auoyde conſent vnto that Idolatri, which Durant and the Papiſte mayntayne and profeſſe, &amp; to deny the Popes cerimonies, the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne whiche we reache, howe ſhuld it not dyſcorage the godly, and incorage the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticious in theyr errors? we can not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defye the Church of Chriſt apparentlye, ſhewinge our ſealues to be on of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes clergye. Seing S. Paull Theſſ. 3. wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lythe to auoyde all apparens of euyll, and to be ſhufflyd in a ſurples, whiche the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes clergye wear, were rather a confuſion then an order, whiche they them ſealues wolde be lothe to ſuffer, if they might get
<pb facs="tcp:13129:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> agayne the keys into theyr handes, they wolde crye withe open mowthe, as theyr pontificall teache them, &amp; plucke the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our backes by the autoryte of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtie God the Father, the Sonne,<note place="margin">The ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples is an holy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Papiſtes.</note> and the Holy ghoſte. ſaying, and we take from the all our clerkly habyt, and we put on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apparell of religion, and depoſe, degrade, and ſpoyle the of all orders clerkely bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and clerkelye lyuinge,<note place="margin">Marke the follye of Papiſtes.</note> and we reſtore the to the ſeruitude and ignominie of the ſecular habyte. Is it not a diſorder, that Chriſtians ſhoulde ſhewe them ſelues ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the Popes order? were it not better to ſerue God in commun attyre, then to pleaſe the Pope by diſquiſinge our ſelues in ſuperſticious ſurpleſſis? were it not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God, who wyllyth vs to ſerue hym in ſpret, and in truthe, then to obey men, followyng the deuyſe of Pope Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſter, the faſſyon of the Iewes, and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe of the Papiſtes: where it not better, by leauynge of a Surples to folow Chriſt in breakynge mens tradicions, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the vſe therof to be a companion of Popes &amp; Phariſes? Yf this do not ſeame ſufficient to proue the Minor at this tyme, it ſhalbe more at large dyſcourſyd hereafter. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quenes Maieſtes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:13129:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> herein we acknowledge our ſealues bownde to obey in all thynges lawfullye commaundyd, ſo can not we be perſuadyd to vſe that in the minyſteri, which our con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences teacheth vs to be repleniſhed with Idolatrous Ipocriſye, &amp; alſo the example of other men which dothe were it, ought nothing at all to moue vs to were a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the minyſterie, no more then to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent with them in perſecutyng thoſe men whom they terme ſedicious ſciſmatyckes for leauyng them of. Thus as ye ſe, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dere Brethren, we leue the ſurples, as the Popes badge to the ſhauen Clergye, and you as Gods choſen to the protection of the almyghtie whyſſhynge, that God may geue vs grace aswell inwardelye as outwardlye, to ſeke for ſyncerite, and to wayght with all pacience the good wyll &amp; pleaſure of the almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, who wyll &amp; can healpe when pleaſith hym. Fare ye well in the Lorde Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13129:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ A Godly Prayer.</head>
            <p>OH Lord God and heauenly Father, which art a iuſt Iudge to puniſhe all them, that do contynewe to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the, as thou art a Father moſt pyty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to receaue to mercy all thoſe, whiche geue ouer themſelues to pleaſe the, ſhewe me thy grace and fauour, ſo that I may be truly touchid withe inward diſpleaſure of my ſynnes, and that in the place of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my ſelf to ſlepe in ſynne, I may be ſo caſt downe in hart, that the rather I may truly with mouthe confeſſe moſt humbly to geue the, the honour, glory, and prayſe, dew vnto thy holy name, and that as thou of thy greate mercy doſte inſtruct vs the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revnto by thy holy word, ſo (for thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſake) make that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame may ſo ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and cleare our conſcience, that in dew examination of all our hole lyffe, we may truly learne to be angry &amp; diſpleaſid with all our former, and corrupte lyuing. Oh that it may pleaſe the to drawe nere vnto vs, in addreſſyng and guydyng our foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes in the true and perfect way of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence to thy holy lawes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Send thy holye Angel to nitche his tentes round about vs, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13129:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> his infernall army, neuer preuayle againſt vs, but allways with ſtrong faith we may thorough Ieſus Chriſt withſtand all his crafty engins and ſnares, knowynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that thou neuer forſakeſt them that put their truſt in the. Oh let vs not be led by the infirmytie of our vntowarde fleſhe, but ſtrenghten vs by the vertue of the holy ſpiryte. Suffer vs not to lye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy heuy wrathe &amp; vengeaunce throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe Ipocryſye, but rather touche vs ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, that we may without ceaſyng, ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe, and grone vnto the, by true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned repentaunce. And althoughe we be not allwayes ſo wel diſpoſyd to aſke &amp; praye, as we ought to do, yet (good Lord) for thy names ſake, ſtretche out thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hande, that by the gratious workyng of thy holy Spirite, our myndes and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes may be drawen from all erthly and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptible thinges, ſo that our prayers may procede of an erneſt and inward affection, ſo that we neuer preſume to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me beſore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with a dobell hart, knowing that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer aſkethe and prayeth for anye thing of the, not aſking in faith, can not obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Increace our faithe therfore (oh mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull Father) that we preſently may ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the benefit of remiſſion and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb facs="tcp:13129:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> or all our ſynnes, thoroughe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes and death of Chriſt Ieſus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and ſo work in vs foreuer hereafter to lyue in thy feare, and to ſtand in awe of thy diſpleaſure, that thou mayſt contynew our mercyfull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world without end. God graunt yt.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
